Guide to the Datus C. Proper Papers 1864-2003
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Datus C. Proper Papers
1864-2003
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Proper, Datus C.
2502
6.4 linear feet
The Datus C. Proper Papers consist of journals, correspondence, family history documents, literary manuscript drafts, galley proofs, research notes, publisher correspondence, photographs and other memorabilia which document Proper's life as a student, United States Foreign Service officer, and outdoor writer. The subjects of Proper's writings encompass the full spectrum of fly fishing for trout, from stream side entomology to the ethics of catch and release angling. Hunting, particularly pheasant hunting and the training of dogs for the sport, is another subject heavily represented.
All literary copyright to the Datus C. Proper papers are the property of Anna Collins-Proper of Belgrade, Montana and permission to publish any material must be granted by her, her heirs or assigns.
The Datus C. Proper papers were donated to Montana State University by Anna Collins-Proper of Belgrade, Montana in January 2009. Additional materials were added to the collection April 2019.
Series 1 Journals, 1951-2002
Series 2 Correspondence, 1985-2002
Series 3 Family papers, 1864-2000
Series 4 Magazine articles, 1965-2002
Series 5 Book publication files, 1992-2002
Series 6 Unfinished book manuscript
Series 7 Subject vertical files
Series 8 Memorial service materials, 2002-2003
Series 9 Photographs
Datus Carryer Proper was born in Des Moines, Iowa on April 18, 1934, the son of William Glisan Proper and Marjorie Carryer Proper. His extended family ancestors included Ida Sedgwick Proper, an early suffragist and New York artist, and Datus DeWitt Proper, an Iowa Civil War veteran and Baptist preacher. Datus C. Proper grew up in Iowa, Nebraska, Northern Minnesota, and Yellowstone National Park, where his father worked as a personnel officer for the Park from 1946 to 1955. Proper attended secondary school at Phillips Exeter Academy in New Hampshire and earned a BA degree in English from Cornell University in 1956. He began a career with the United States Foreign Service and served in Washington D.C., Angola, Brazil, Ireland and Portugal as a political analyst. He also earned a MA degree from George Washington University in 1978 and completed the course of study at the National War College during the same year. His longtime interest in fly fishing and pheasant hunting were sharpened during his government career, and he experienced success in publishing sporting articles along with his first book, What The Trout Said, prior to his retirement from the State Department in 1987. Proper then moved with his family to the Gallatin Valley near Bozeman, Montana where he began a full time career as a writer, mostly on outdoor subjects. He wrote three more books during his time in Montana and hundreds of articles for outdoor and regional magazines, especially Field and Stream where he became a regular contributor. He married Anna Therese Collins in 1975 and had two sons prior to his death on July 27, 2003.
The Datus C. Proper papers consist of journals, correspondence, family history documents, literary manuscript drafts, galley proofs, research notes, publisher correspondence, photographs and other memorabilia which document Proper's life as a student, United States Foreign Service officer, and outdoor writer. His family history documents feature materials pertaining to Proper's extended family ancestors, including notes and clippings about Ida Sedgwick Proper, and the Civil War diary of Datus DeWitt Proper, corporal, 19th Iowa Volunteer Infantry. Datus Proper's journals document his early interest in fly fishing and hunting, containing both diary-like entries and miscellaneous notes that he later used in his published writings. The manuscript drafts encompass many, but not all, of Proper's articles for magazines like Field and Stream, and his four full length books. A research vertical file of clippings and miscellaneous notes maintained by Proper for reference purposes has also been preserved within this collection, along with a small collection of photographs, some of which were used to illustrate Proper's published articles. The subjects of Proper's writings encompass the full spectrum of fly fishing for trout, from stream side entomology to the ethics of catch and release angling. Hunting, particularly pheasant hunting and the training of dogs for the sport, is another subject heavily represented. Proper also wrote on Portugal, a country in which he had served during his career with the State Department, and in addition to his writings he saved some letters and documents written in Portuguese. Correspondents found in this collection include Vince Marinaro, Nick Lyons, Paul Schullery, and other prominent fly fishing and hunting writers. Oversize materials include topographical maps marked with locations of Proper's hunting and fishing trips, certificates and awards, and tracings of fish that Proper caught and measured.
Lyons, Nick-Correspondence; Marinaro, Vincent-Correspondence; Proper, Datus C-Archives; Proper, Datus DeWitt, 1844-1922-Diaries; Proper, Ida Sedgwick, 1873-1957; Schullery, Paul-Correspondence; Proper, Datus C., Last old place; Proper, Datus C., Pheasants of the mind; Proper, Datus C., Running waters; Proper, Datus C., What the trout said; Proper, Datus DeWitt, 1844-1922
Phillips Exeter Academy-Students; United States-Army-Iowa Infantry Regiment, 19th (1862-1865); United States-Foreign Service-Officials and employees
Proper, Datus C-Family
Iowa-History-Civil War, 1861-1865; Portugal; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives
Authors and publishers; Fishers--Diaries; Fly fishing; Hunters--Diaries; Hunting; Hunting dogs-Training; Pheasant shooting; Soldiers-United States-Diaries; Fishers; Hunters; Outdoor writers-Montana
Elementary and Secondary Education; Fishing and Canning; Military; Publishers and Publishing; Photographs
Diaries; Family papers; Manuscripts for publication; Photographs
- Journals, 1951-2002; 1
  Proper's journals document his hunting and fishing experiences and feature entries related to his article and book ideas. Proper's earliest fishing journal dates from 1951 and documents trout fishing while a student in New Hampshire. The bulk of his journals date from Proper's active writing career between 1965 and 2003, and detail his experiences fishing and hunting in Brazil, Portugal, Ireland, Montana, and elsewhere in the United States. The inclusive dates for each journal are approximate, and many diaries have laid-in notes placed by Proper in reference to his magazine article compositions.
  - Journal, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Journal, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journal, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Journal, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Journal, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journal, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journal, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Journal, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journal, 1998-2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Journal, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Journal, Various Dates (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 2
  This series only represents those letters that Proper kept in a separate file sequence. Other letters specifically related to individual writings by Proper can be found interfiled with his various manuscript drafts in series 5-9. The letters have been arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name, with more substantial groups of letters, or those with enclosures that would be confused in as a group arrangement, assigned to individually named folders.
  Proper's correspondence files feature incoming and outgoing letters with publishers, readers, reviewers, family, friends, and other sportsmen. The bulk of the correspondence relates to Proper's writing career and includes feedback from readers and editors, hunting and fishing tips exchanged with friends and colleagues, and information requests from Proper to other writers and sportsmen. Proper maintained these files during his lifetime, and created generic alphabetical groupings based on correspondent name or created individual files for more frequent correspondents.
  - A (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alberda, Rudi van (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - B (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bachman, Robert A. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Behnke, Robert J. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bramley, Alan (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Brandabur, Jack (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Burger, Knox (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - C (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Club Francais des Pecheurs a la Mouche (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - D (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - E (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - F (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Field & Stream editors, etc. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - G (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gaertner, Susanna (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - H (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Heddon, Jack (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - I, J, K (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Kelly, William H. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - L (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lyons, Nick (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - M (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Maguire, Nan (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Marinaro, Vince (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Martin, Darrel (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Montana, State of (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - N, O (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Outdoor Writers Association (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - P (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Parks, Richard (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Parry, Joseph (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pequegnot, J.P. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pereira, Carlos (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pride, Ralph (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Q, R (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - S (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Schullery, Paul (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - T (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Tapply, William G. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Umpqua Feather Merchants (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - W (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Wellington, Herb (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Zinn, David (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Family Papers, 1864-2000; 3
  Proper's family papers document his personal life and family history. They include several personal items from his childhood including a baby book, school ephemera from Exeter Academy, student essays, and report cards. They also include a small amount of family correspondence and records documenting his career as a Foreign Service officer at the State Department. Records documenting his family history include genealogical records and collected items and biographies of Proper's distant relatives Datus Dewitt Proper (1844-1922), Ida Sedgwick Proper (1876-1957), and Datus Edwin Proper (1896-1965). Among these collected items is a Civil War diary written by Datus Dewitt Proper between 1864 and 1865, documenting his service in Louisiana, Alabama, and Florida.
  - Autobiographical information (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Babyhood Days" record book (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Term grade reports, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report cards, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous elementary and high school papers (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exeter Academy printed ephemera (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Family letters, 1946-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - State Department performance evaluations and correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - State Department-Vietnam protest, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Student essays (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Genealogy charts (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy notes (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Datus Edwin Proper (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ida Sedgwick Proper (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Datus DeWitt Proper-diary, 1864-1865 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Datus DeWitt Proper-letters, 1864-1865 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Datus DeWitt Proper-"Pioneer and Missionary Experiences" (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Magazine articles, 1965-2002; 4
  Proper's article and manuscript drafts are arranged into three distinct groups. The first grouping was established by Proper and arranges articles by topic. Proper maintained drafts for several different compositions in these topical files. Along with the various drafts Proper placed handwritten notes, letters of submission to publishers, galley proofs, and occasionally tear sheets of printed articles. All of the subject labeled files bear titles Proper originally assigned to them. Other manuscript files were originally unorganized and have been arranged by working title, whether or not that title was chosen for the final published version. Files in this group mostly contain the draft manuscript, but also contain publisher correspondence in a few cases. There is a significant amount of duplication between this group and the first, but the various draft versions often bear handwritten corrections and alterations making the retention of both necessary to demonstrate the author's composition process. Finally, Proper kept a small collection of tear sheets of his various published articles that is far from complete, along with a few clippings that mentioned him as a writer and outdoorsman. A prolific writer, Proper did not maintain a comprehensive list of his publication output, making the task of reconstructing his bibliography difficult at best. The articles have been grouped in alphabetic folders representing the titles. All of the folders in this series have been alphabetically arranged, with the sequence repeated for each of the three groups.
  Proper's magazine articles include manuscript drafts, galley proofs, notes, publisher correspondence, research letters, and a partial physical bibliography of Proper's magazine publications. Proper's drafts touch on a wide range of topics including fishing, fly tying, dogs, hunting, game birds, cooking wild game, wilderness, and life in the outdoors.
  - Air Guns (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Beepers (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Blue Grouse (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Brook Trout (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Brown Trout (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cooking/Pheasants (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CRPs (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dog Ideas (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Doves (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Early Stories (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Field & Stream Surveys (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Fishing Questionnaire (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Flops (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Fly Design Presentation (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fly Tying and Flies (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gambel's Quail (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Game Guns (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Grouse (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Hooks (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Huck (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Hunting Philosophy (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Inter-Fluve, Inc. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Marinaro (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Hunting and Dogs (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mearns Quail (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ortega Foreword (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pheasants (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pheasants (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Quail in Arizona (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Read My Nose (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Right Brain (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Robertson/Venison Choke Cherries (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Rock Creek (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Scotty's Story (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sharptails (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Shorts (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Shunning Books (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Snipe (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Fly (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Splash/Stoneflies (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Wendy Schweizer (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Adriano and the Rattlesnakes" (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Angloholism" (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "Another Time and Place" (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Artist With a Fly Rod" (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "Bailey's Secrets" (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Beavers" (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "The Best of It" (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - "Big John" (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - "Big Sky Carvers" (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - "Brown Partridges and Blue Winged Olives" (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - "Catch and Release" (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - "Change Levels" (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - "Dai-Riki Tippet Material" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Dark Hollow" (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Deer and Pheasants in Montana" (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "The Dry Fly in Portugal" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Escaping Gravity" (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Faith in a Fly" (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Farming" (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Feeding Frenzy" (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Fishing the Geology" (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Fishing Thompson's Spring Creek" (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Fishing With The Ouzels" (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Floating Down The River" (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Happy Birthday Nymph" (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "How I Trained Patch" (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Inside the Hidden Hatch" (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Introduction-Dry Fly Code" (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Leave a Kid Home Today" (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "The Long Hunt" (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "Lunch by the Stream" (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "Managing Eden" (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "The Mayfly Murders" (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "Nature Shock" (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - "The Nature of Life" (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "The News From Mount Olympus" (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Nobody Tells You To Sit Still" (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "A Place of Our Own" (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "The Rattlesnake Hole" (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "Respect" (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "Run Free, Yellowstone" (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "Scoring" (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - "Something Old, Something New" (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - "Tender Venison" (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - "Tools for the Outdoors" (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - "Trout Management in the United States" (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - "Two Kinds of Trout Fishing" (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - "Up the Mountain and Into the Woods" (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - "Water and the West" (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - "Wet and Dry" (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - "Yellowstone Cutthroats" (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - The First Time (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Articles "A" (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Articles "B" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Articles "C" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Articles "D-E" (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Articles "F" (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Articles "G-K" (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Articles "L-M" (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Articles "N-P" (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Articles "Q-R" (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Articles "S-U" (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Articles "T-Y" (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Articles about Datus C. Proper (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Book Publication Files, 5
  The folders are arranged in the order in which Proper published his books.
  Proper's book publication files document the production of his four published books: What the Trout Said (1982; rev. ed. 1989); Pheasants of the Mind (1990; rev. ed. 1994); The Last Old Place: A Search Through Portugal (1992); and Running Waters (2001). Each draft combined portions of previously published essays with new original compositions. These files contain manuscript drafts, publisher correspondence, published book reviews, reader's letters, and notes pertaining to each book.
  - What the Trout Said - reviews, first edition (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - What the Trout Said - reviews, second edition (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - What the Trout Said - reviews, second edition revisions (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - What the Trout Said - reviews, leftovers (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - What the Trout Said - contracts, misc. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Pheasants of the Mind - reviews (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Pheasants of the Mind - contracts, misc. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Last Old Place - reviews and letters (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Last Old Place - Contracts, etc. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - The Last Old Place - Excerpts (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - The Last Old Place - Illustrations (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Running Waters - title and introduction (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Running Waters - Part 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Running Waters - Part 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Running Waters - Part 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Running Waters - Part 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Running Waters - contract, misc. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Unfinished book manuscript, 6
  The arrangement of these folders begins with Proper's initial inquiries on the project and introduction, and then a month by month listing of the work he did on the individual chapters. The folders bear the original labels assigned by Proper, and no attempt was made to consolidate materials that were kept in duplicate titles in order to preserve evidential value.
  Proper's unfinished book manuscript features chapter drafts from a book he began working on during the end of his life titled variously as "The Home Place" or simply "Home." The book draws from Proper's previously published articles and attempts to examine his personal relationship with nature and how his chosen lifestyle had been affected by the land and the elements. The manuscript is organized into twelve chapters named after the months of the year and address broader themes such as home building in an environmentally sensitive area, hunting, fishing, and mankind's ever-changing relationship with nature. Proper intended to use many of his earlier magazine articles as a basis for each chapter and named the chapter title drafts the months of the year. He annotated the composition with comments about where to cut certain passages, add other passages, and consider other chapters where the composition might be better placed. Throughout his writing and editing process, Proper solicited feedback from his agent, Knox Burger, and other readers, and included their suggestions in with his drafts. As a result, there is a great deal of repetition between the contents of this incomplete manuscript and Proper's published articles.
  - Introductory (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - January (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - January (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - February (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - March (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - March (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - March - Dogs (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - March - Streambed Repair (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - April (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - April (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - May (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - May/June - Utopia (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - May/June - Church and State (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - June (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - June - Romanticism (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - July (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - July (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - August (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - September (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - September (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - September - Prairies (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - October (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - October (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - November (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - November - Pheasants at Home (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - December (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - December (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Subject Vertical Files, 7
  The files were organized alphabetically under broad subject headings. In addition to the original folders A small set of notes contained in the Outdoor and Miscellaneous section were loose or laid in books from Proper's personal library and have been grouped in categories by the archivist. Processors have identified the volumes from which these various scraps were taken in order to assist researchers in placing the material in context. The present arrangement preserves the original order of these files, arranged alphabetically under the major subject divisions.
  Proper's subject vertical files feature topical files maintained by Proper in support of research for his publications. The files relate to topics of interest to Proper including fly fishing, hunting, streams and rivers, dogs, guns, and wild game. Although most files contain little more than printed materials, occasionally Proper would place letters or notes he felt relevant to the folder's title.
  - Dogs: Field Trials, Collars (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dogs: Scent, Confirmation and Coat, Origin and History (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Dogs: Temperament, Breeds, Care (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Dogs: Testing, Puppies (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Flies-Natural and Artificial and Other Trout Foods: Alders, Craneflies, Black Gnats, Moths (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Flies-Natural and Artificial and Other Trout Foods: Damselflies, Dragonflies (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Flies-Natural and Artificial and Other Trout Foods: Insect Habitat and Behavior (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Flies-Natural and Artificial and Other Trout Foods: Mayflies - Natural and Imitation (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Flies-Natural and Artificial and Other Trout Foods: Midges (Box 12, Folder 9)